<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Links | Rushing Avian Ecology Lab</title>
    <link>/links/</link>
      <atom:link href="/links/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Links</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Links</title>
      <link>/links/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code of conduct</title>
      <link>/links/coc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/links/coc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All members of the Rushing lab are expected to behave in a manner that promotes a healthy, inclusive working environment. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be kind to others. Treat members of the lab as you would want to be treated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep all communication appropriate for a professional audience. Sexual or discriminatory language and imagery is not appropriate at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do your part to create a respectful environment for everyone. Every member of this lab has something to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that your actions can inadvertently be injurious to others even if you do not intend them to be. If someone calls you out on your behavior, please listen to them, apologize, and learn from the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discrimination or harassment of any kind will not be tolerated. This includes but is not limited to discrimination based on: racial or ethnic background, citizenship status, religion, political affiliation, gender identity/expression, sexual orientation, dis/ability status, or appearance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any instances of inappropriate behavior should be reported to Clark Rushing or the the appropriate authorities immediately. All communications will be treated as confidential. Any lab member that is asked to stop inappropriate behavior is expected to comply immediately. Failure to comply will result referral to the appropriate University authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sexual-harassment-and-assualt&#34;&gt;Sexual harassment and assualt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Georgia takes issues related to sexual harassment and assault very seriously. From the UGA &lt;a href=&#34;https://eoo.uga.edu/policies-resources/ndah-policy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;non-discrimination and anti-harassment policy webpage&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sexual Misconduct&lt;/strong&gt;:  An umbrella term that is used to describe a wide range of prohibited sexual conduct as described below, including sexual harassment. Sexual misconduct can occur regardless of the relationship, position or respective sex, sexual orientation, or gender identity of the parties. Same-sex harassment violates this Policy, as does harassment by a student of an employee or a subordinate employee of their supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sexual Harassment&lt;/strong&gt; (Other than Student on Student): Unwelcome verbal, nonverbal, or physical conduct, based on sex (including gender stereotypes), that may be any of the following:
- Implicitly or explicitly a term or condition of employment or status in a course, program, or activity;
- A basis for employment or educational decisions;
- Is sufficiently severe, persistent, or pervasive to interfere with one’s work or educational performance creating an intimidating, hostile, or offensive work or learning environment, or interfering with or limiting one’s ability to participate in or to benefit from an institutional program or activity; or
- Determined by a Reasonable Person to be so severe, pervasive, and objectively offensive that it effectively denies a person equal access to a University education program or activity in violation of Title IX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sexual Harassment&lt;/strong&gt; (Student on Student): Unwelcome verbal, nonverbal, or physical conduct based on sex (including gender stereotypes), determined by a Reasonable Person to be so severe, pervasive, and objectively offensive that it effectively denies a person equal access to participate in or to benefit from an institutional education program or activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about how to report a sexual assault incident and resources if you have been the victim of sexual assault, please refer to the University&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://safeandsecure.uga.edu/sexual-assault/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Preventing and Responding to Sexual Assault&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that when reporting incidents of sexual assault or harassment, UGA &lt;a href=&#34;https://eoo.uga.edu/policies-resources/title-ix-sex-discrimination-harassment/sexual-assault-response-protocol/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;offers amnesty&lt;/a&gt; for the drug and alcohol student code violations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material in this document was inspired by and borrows from the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BahlaiLab/Policies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bahlai Lab Policies&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; by Dr. Christie Bahlai and her lab group, used under CC BY 4.0. The Rushing Lab policies are licensed under CC BY 4.0 by Dr. Clark Rushing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mentoring philosophy</title>
      <link>/links/mentoring_philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/links/mentoring_philosophy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No matter where you are in your career, academia can feel a bit like back-country orienteering. You pick a destination far off in the distance, make a plan for getting there, and then set off into the wilderness. In some places, especially early on, there may be well-worn trails. But as you go further, you will increasingly have to blaze your own path. The going is often tough. There may be times when you need to stop, figure out where you are, and reassess your plans. But with planning and a good support system, most destinations can be reached and the journey will be worth the effort. Although cheesy, I think this metaphor provides a good basis for my mentoring philosophy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-role&#34;&gt;My role&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe strongly that as an adviser, my job is to help students figure out where they want to go, to equip them with the right tools to get there, and to make sure they don&amp;rsquo;t get too lost along the way. My job is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to choose my students&#39; destinations for them or enforce a specific path. To this end, I strive to work with each lab member to establish long-term ambitions, shorter-term goals, and a roadmap for achieving these objectives. The degree of assistance that each student needs will vary as a function of previous experience, career goals, and self-sufficiency. Regardless, my primary role is to understand the needs of my students and provide them with the support they require to advance their career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course my career, I have found that my most productive relationships are based on respect, humility, hard work, and humor. These are traits that I strive to bring to the lab. They are also the traits I look for in collaborators and students. Members of my lab can expect me to provide a supportive, respectful working environment and above all I expect all lab members to &lt;a href=&#34;links/code-of-conduct.html&#34;&gt;contribute positively&lt;/a&gt; to this atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-docs&#34;&gt;Post-docs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-docs are at a transitional phase in their career: still under the supervision of a mentor but expected to demonstrate the ability to conduct research as an independent scientist. The primary purpose of doing a post-doc is, in my opinion, to get a permanent job, not to pad the CV of your mentor. Therefore, I view post-docs in may lab as collaborators rather than employees or students. Early in your post-doc, we will establish a set of deliverables for the project that is funding your fellowship and a plan for carrying out the research. We will also discuss your career goals and identify opportunities to strengthen your CV in areas that will help you land a job. I may lean on you from time-to-time to help with teaching or mentoring duties but you should focus first and foremost on publishing papers, getting grants, and applying for jobs. Where applicable, we will work together to design new projects and find additional funding. If at any point during your post-doc you get offered a job that you want, TAKE IT! Whatever project you&amp;rsquo;re working on for me will survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;graduate-students&#34;&gt;Graduate students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expectations for graduate students enrolled in Warnell&amp;rsquo;s MS and PhD programs are outlined in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.warnell.uga.edu/graduate/current-students/advisory-committee-and-program-study&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;graduate student handbook&lt;/a&gt;. This document also contains useful information and advice for being successful in this department. Additional resources for completing your degree, including a checklist of degree completion requirements for both the MS and PhD programs, can be found on the School&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.warnell.uga.edu/sites/default/files/inline-files/PHD%20Checklist.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. This checklist will serve as the primary guide for developing individual expectations within the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the degree completion requirements, I recognize that individual students have different expectations and objectives both during and after graduate school. My role as a mentor is to help you formulate and meet those objectives. For this reason, I will meet with each student in my lab early in your first semester and then on a regular basis to discuss expectations, goals, and progress. During these meetings we will develop a mentoring plan that establishes shared objectives, timelines, and deliverables. This plan may (and will likely) change over the course of your graduate career but will serve as blueprint for us to establish your personal goals and a defined path for progress and evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;undergraduate-students&#34;&gt;Undergraduate students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting involved in on-going research projects or establishing independent projects with the help of a faculty mentor are great ways for undergraduates to gets hands-on research experience, deepen their understanding of scientific concepts, and become more competitive for jobs or graduate school.
I am happy to help interested students plan, implement, and communicate independent research projects. I plan to establish several local field projects that focus on the ecology of birds in and around Athens. These projects could provide numerous opportunities for independent research by students interested in ornithology, population ecology, behavior, and statistical modeling. If you are interested in the work done my lab and would like to get involved in undergraduate research, please contact me about research and funding opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-idwork_life_balanceaa-note-on-work-life-balance&#34;&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;work_life_balance&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A note on work-life balance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academia is stressful. Social isolation, imposter syndrome, and competitive job markets all contribute to high rates of mental health issues in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2018/03/06/new-study-says-graduate-students-mental-health-crisis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;graduate students&lt;/a&gt;. Although some stress is unavoidable, suffering from mental health issues is not inevitable. Spending time with family, finding activities that help you recharge your batteries, and taking time off are all important strategies for maintaining mental and physical health. These activities also tend to boost long-term productivity. One of the reasons for developing a individual mentoring plan is so that we can judge your progress based on explicit expectations and goals rather than proxies like hours spent in the lab. We will meet on a regular basis to make sure you are on the right track and I do expect students to make steady progress. However, as long as you are making progress towards your degree, when and how you work does not make much difference to me. If you work best early in the morning, late at night, or during the weekend, that&amp;rsquo;s fine. If you can get everything done M-Th, take long weekends. Bottom line, find the schedule that works best for you and go with it. I pledge to encourage members of my lab to have a healthy life outside of the office and to lead by example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also recognize that a healthy work-life balance may not, by itself, be enough. If you are in my lab and feel like you are struggling with mental health issues, please come talk to me. We will work together to find help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material in this document was inspired by and borrows from the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BahlaiLab/Policies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bahlai Lab Policies&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; by Dr. Christie Bahlai and her lab group, used under CC BY 4.0. The Rushing Lab policies are licensed under CC BY 4.0 by Dr. Clark Rushing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prospective students</title>
      <link>/links/prospective_students/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/links/prospective_students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;phd-assistantship-pinyon-jay-habitat-use-and-movement-ecology&#34;&gt;PhD assistantship, Pinyon Jay habitat use and movement ecology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location – Athens, GA with fieldwork in Utah and New Mexico&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salary - $30,000 per year plus tuition, fees, and benefits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start Date – January 10th, 2022 (preferred)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last Date To Apply – September 24th, 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently seeking applicants for a PhD assistantship (4 years, fully funded) available in the Warnell School of Forestry and Natural Resources at the University of Georgia to study Pinyon Jay (&lt;em&gt;Gymnorhinus cyanocephalus&lt;/em&gt;) habitat use and movement ecology in response to piñon-juniper woodland treatments. Students from under-represented groups in wildlife fields are strongly encouraged to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Piñon-juniper woodland treatments are common throughout the western United States, though the effects of these treatments on Pinyon Jays, a species undergoing rapid population declines across its range, are poorly understood. This study will provide land management agencies critical information about impacts of woodland management on Pinyon Jays, as well as produce significant, novel data about habitat use, movement, and life history of the species. These data will allow land managers to better understand the needs of the species and inform how future management practices can be implemented to reduce or mitigate negative impacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The selected student will be expected to conduct fieldwork at multiple locations throughout the state of Utah and northern New Mexico. Fieldwork will include: conducting grid-based point counts, capturing and banding jays, deploying tracking tags using conventional harness-style attachments, and possibly performing colony counts. The student will also be expected the analyze multiple types of data using modern statistical methods and communicate project results to multiple audiences, including the scientific community, agency staff, and the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preference will be given to candidates who can enroll for the spring 2022 semester. The successful applicant will receive a $30,000 per year stipend (12-month). Tuition is also covered and the student will receive either direct bill payments or a stipend supplement to cover at least 75% of the student portion of university fees and health insurance. The student will be advised by Dr. Clark Rushing at the University of Georgia, while working closely with collaborators at the Utah Division of Wildlife Resources and the US Fish &amp;amp; Wildlife Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;qualifications&#34;&gt;Qualifications:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B.S. degree in wildlife biology, management, ecology, or related discipline&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.S. degree in wildlife biology, management, ecology, or related discipline strongly preferred.  GRE scores are not required&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrated experience capturing and banding birds, including attachment of tracking tags&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrated experience collecting and analyzing ecological data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent written and verbal communication skills&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong interest in quantitative techniques and spatial ecology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experience in R is strongly preferred&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this position will require the ability to legally operate state-owned vehicles in off-road conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested applicants should submit the following documents as a single PDF or word document to Dr. Clark Rushing (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:clark.rushing@uga.edu&#34;&gt;clark.rushing@uga.edu&lt;/a&gt;) by September 24th, 2021:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.5-page (max) cover letter summarizing your interest in the position, qualifications, and experience, as well as research and career aspirations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curriculum Vitae&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An applicant-led writing sample (e.g., thesis chapter, publication)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unofficial academic transcripts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Names and contact information for three professional references&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, students with their own funding are welcome to reach out to me about joining the lab. I am happy to advise students working on a variety of topics related to ornithology, quantitative ecology, and conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-note-on-quantitative-skills-for-prospective-students&#34;&gt;A note on quantitative skills for prospective students&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecology is an inherently quantitative field and it is becoming nearly impossible to be a practicing ecologist without some training in statistics and programming. The research done in my lab reflects these realities and I want all of my students to graduate with a toolbox of quantitative skills that will allow them to be successful professionals. I do not, however, require new students to arrive on campus with extensive experience in these areas. More important to me is a desire to learn quantitative skills and apply them to exciting scientific questions. At the end of the day, if you can formulate good questions and are willing to put in the time to learn how to answer them, you will be a successful scientist. So if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the types of questions that we ask in the Rushing lab but don&amp;rsquo;t consider yourself a quantitative ecologist, don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to contact me about joining the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
