<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Painted buntings | Rushing Population Ecology Lab</title>
    <link>/tag/painted-buntings/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/painted-buntings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Painted buntings</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Painted buntings</title>
      <link>/tag/painted-buntings/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passerina buntings</title>
      <link>/project/passerina/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/passerina/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Species in the genus &lt;em&gt;Passerina&lt;/em&gt; are among the most charismatic birds in North America. They are also ideally suited for studying the full-annual-cycle ecology of migratory songbirds because several species can be efficiently captured and monitored at bird feeders throughout the year. For the past several years, I have worked with colleagues from the Smithsonian Migratory Bird Center and the Cornell Lab of Ornithology to better understand the migration ecology, migratory connectivity, and winter distrubution of southeastern Painted Buntings (&lt;em&gt;Passerina ciris&lt;/em&gt;) across their breeding range. To date, we have deployed nearly 300 light-level geolocators on buntings at 6 study sites spanning the latitudinal distribution of this population (northern Florida to southern North Carolina). In the spring of 2019, we established a network of RFID-enabled bird feeders to collect encounter data from buntings at each of our study sites. These data will provide critical information about seasonal survival of Painted Buntings, as well as how survival varies spatially and seasonally.&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-photo-by-kim-savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/lazb.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Photo by Kim Savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/lazb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Photo by Kim Savides
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also starting in the spring of 2019, we expanded this research to include Lazuli Buntings (&lt;em&gt;Passerina amoeba&lt;/em&gt;) breeding in and around Logan, UT. This project uses similar tracking and RFID technologies to quantify migratory connectivity, molting/winter grounds, and survival of Lazuli Buntings along a large elevational gradient. During the summer of 2020, our 18 RFID feeders recorded over 300,000 visits by about 250 banded birds! These data are allowing us to quantify arrival and departure phenology of these populations with a high degree of precision and in the future will allow us to estimate survival and density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually we hope the data collected as part of these projects will provide insights into how breeding and non-breeding processes influence vital rates and population dynamics and whether life-history theory provides a cogent framework for understanding full annual cycle limitation in migratory birds. Stay tuned for exciting results coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Full annual cycle models</title>
      <link>/project/fac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/fac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Historically, efforts to identify limiting factors for migratory species have been hindered by the scale of annual migration movements, missing information about the geographic linkages between breeding and non-breeding populations (i.e., migratory connectivity), and the lack of analytical methods for linking population dynamics to demographic processes operating across the entire annual cycle. A major theme of my research focuses on application technological advances and developing ‘full-annual-cycle’ population models to overcome these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major challenges to understanding limiting factors of migratory birds has long been the scientists have not known where specific populations go after they leave the breeding or wintering grounds. Information about migration routes, winter distribution, and migration phenology is currently unavailable for many species because, until recently, over 40% of migratory bird species were too small track using even the most advanced satellite tags. A major focus of my research has been using new technologies, including stable isotopes (Rushing et al. 2014 Ecol Apps; Rushing et al. 2017 Ecol &amp;amp; Evol) and miniaturized tracking tags, to better understand the migratory connectivity of small songbirds (Cohen et al. 2018 MEE). Current work on this topic includes two projects that are using light-level geolocators to determine the migratory connectivity and non-breeding distribution of &lt;a href=&#34;project/passerina.md&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Passerina&lt;/em&gt; buntings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to quantifying patterns of migratory connectivity, much of my research focuses on developing &amp;lsquo;full-annual-cycle&amp;rsquo; models to link population dynamics of migratory birds to demographic and environmental processes occurring through the year. Full-annual-cycle models include a broad range of modeling frameworks (Hosttetler et al. 2015) and I regularly use several of these methods in my research, including Bayesian hierarchical models and integrated population models (IPMs). Some of my work on full-annual-cycle models has focused on exploring how breeding vs. winter habitat contribute to spatial variation in population trajectories in Wood Thrush (Rushing et al. 2016b Proc B), estimating seasonal survival rates by integrating breeding and winter capture-recapture data (Rushing 2019 Ecol &amp;amp; Evol), and using IPMs to link changes in Wood Thrush breeding abundance to reproduction, immigration and seasonal survival (Rushing et al. 2017b Ecology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the importance of full-annual-cycle models for advancing our understanding of the ecology of migratory birds, continued work on developing and expanding these frameworks is the central aim of my current research. Ongoing projects on this topic include: improving methods to estimate fall and spring migration survival and their relation to climate, habitat, and density; developing population viability analyses that can used to predict the effects of breeding vs. non-breeding management options; and developing a theoretical framework for predicting when and why populations should be breeding vs. non-breeding limited. In the coming years, our projects on migratory connectivity and variation in life-history strategies of &lt;em&gt;Passerina&lt;/em&gt; buntings will produce data for testing these theoretical predictions. Ultimately, it is my hope that these efforts can be used to improve management and conservation outcomes for the many species of declining migratory birds across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;relevant-publications-pdf-available-upon-request&#34;&gt;Relevant publications (pdf available upon request):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C. S. 2019. Estimability of migration survival rates from integrated breeding and winter capture–recapture data. &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, 9(2), 849-858.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Hostetler, J.A., Sillett, T.S., Marra, P.P., Rotenberg, J.A. and Ryder, T.B., 2017. Spatial and temporal drivers of avian population dynamics across the annual cycle. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt;, 98(11), 2837-2850.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Ryder, T.B. and Marra, P.P., 2016. Quantifying drivers of population dynamics for a migratory bird throughout the annual cycle. &lt;em&gt;Proc. R. Soc. B&lt;/em&gt;, 283(1823), 20152846.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Ryder, T.B., Saracco, J.F. and Marra, P.P., 2014. Assessing migratory connectivity for a long‐distance migratory bird using multiple intrinsic markers. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Applications&lt;/em&gt;, 24(3), 445-456.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen, E.B., Hostetler, J.A., Hallworth, M.T., Rushing, C.S., Sillett, T.S. and Marra, P.P., 2018. Quantifying the strength of migratory connectivity. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, 9(3), 513-524.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen, E.B., Rushing, C.R., Moore, F.R., Hallworth, M.T., Hostetler, J.A., Ramirez, M.G. and Marra, P.P., 2018. The strength of migratory connectivity for birds en route to breeding through the Gulf of Mexico. &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RFID</title>
      <link>/project/rfid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/rfid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, studying individual birds has been a labor-intensive process. Individuals must be captured, given unique marks (e.g., metal and colored plastic leg bands), and then re-captured or re-sighted during future study periods. Re-capturing and re-sighting efforts, in particular, tend to be expensive, time-consumiing, and often have low detection probabilities. A growing part our lab&amp;rsquo;s research is focused on the use of Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) technology to overcome these obstacles and advance our understanding of the demography and behavior of migratory birds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-is-rfid&#34;&gt;What is RFID?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio-frequency_identification&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RFID&lt;/a&gt; is a widespread technology that uses electromagnetic fields to identify coded tags that are attached to individual organisms or objects. It is the exact same technology that is used to chip pets and record times in a marathon. RFID networks consist of four components: 1) a transponder tag attached to each individual, 2) an antenna for receiving data from each transponder tag, 3) a tag-reading device that interprets and logs the data from each tag, and 4) a power source. In most wildlife studies that use RFID, the reader, antenna, and power source are placed in a location where individuals from the study population will reliably visit. Individuals are marked with passive integrated transponder (PIT) tags, which provide a unique ID code for each individual. When marked individuals are within range of the antenna, the reader logs the ID and time of the visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-do-you-use-rfid-to-study-birds&#34;&gt;How do you use RFID to study birds?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RFID networks used in most ornithogical research have relatively small read ranges (~2-6cm). As a result, use of this technology requires placing the antenna and reader in a location that birds are likely to visit, including nest boxes and bird feeders. For our research, we have specially chosen several species that regularly visit bird feeders during either their breeding or winter period. This allows us to locate the RFID antennas on the feeder perches, ensuring that individuals will be within a few centimeters of the antenna while they eat. The reader and a small battery are housed under or next to the feeder in a waterproof box and a solar panel is attached to the feeder stand to provide continuous power.&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-rfid-feeder&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/feeder.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;RFID feeder&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/feeder.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    RFID feeder
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because PIT tags need no battery, they are small and widely available as bird bands. Once the RFID network is installed on a feeder, we band individual birds using that feeder, giving each bird an aluminum USGS band and a PIT band. Both bands have a unique numeric code (physically etched into the metal band, stored as part of the transponder in the PIT band), allowing us to individually identify each bird when we encounter it at future points in time. &lt;strong&gt;Please be aware that all banding activities, including capturing birds and attaching auxillary leg bands, are carried out by trained professionals with all state and federal permits&lt;/strong&gt;. After a bird is banded, it is released unharmed and the reader will log every subsequent visit that individual makes to the feeder. These &amp;ldquo;encounter histories&amp;rdquo; provide data that can be used to estimate ecological parameters that are central to our research questions (e.g., survival probability, arrival/departure dates, activity levels, etc.) using well-established statistical models.&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-pit-tagged-lazuli-bunting-photo-by-kim-savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/rfid_lazb.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;PIT tagged Lazuli Bunting. Photo by Kim Savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/rfid_lazb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    PIT tagged Lazuli Bunting. Photo by Kim Savides
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rfid-projects-in-our-lab&#34;&gt;RFID projects in our lab&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;painted-buntings&#34;&gt;Painted Buntings&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2019, we installed RFID feeders at several of long-term Painted Bunting (&lt;em&gt;Passerina ciris&lt;/em&gt;) field sites in Florida, Georgia, South Carolina, and North Carolina. Over the next two summers, these feeders logged nearly 100,000 unique visits by about 150 tagged individuals. In the future, we plan to expand this feeder network within and beyond these sites to better understand survival, phenology, and density of Painted Buntings within the eastern population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lazuli-buntings&#34;&gt;Lazuli Buntings&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Painted Buntings, the closely-related Lazuli Bunting (&lt;em&gt;Passerina amoena&lt;/em&gt;) is one of the most charismatic migratory birds in the American West. In autumn, individuals migrate to northern Mexico where they molt during monsoonal rains before moving further south for the winter. Lazuli Buntings are also one of the most common migratory songbirds breeding in Cache Valley, Utah and can be found across a wide elevational range, from the valley floor (~1400m) to the high peaks of the Bear River Range (~3000m). During the spring and summer of 2019, we established a network of RFID feeders at 3 sites that span this elevational gradient. During the summers of 2019 and 2020, these feeders recorded nearly 400,000 unique visits by several hundred banded buntings. We are currently using these data to estimate elevational variation in the migration phenology of male and female buntings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;black-rosy-finches&#34;&gt;Black Rosy-finches&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black Rosy-finches (&lt;em&gt;Leucosticte atrata&lt;/em&gt;) are one of three species of Rosy-finch in North America. Utah is at the heart of the Black Rosy-finch distribution. Due to their small range and inaccessible breeding habitat, Black Rosy-finches are one of the least-studied birds in North America. As such, the future well-being of Rosy-finches is hampered by an absence of even basic information about the demography, distribution, and movement of this species. Filling crucial data gaps about Black Rosy-finches distribution and abundance is especially critical to ensure that their populations can be sustained in the face of habitat degradation and climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In winter, flocks of Black Rosy-finches and Gray-crowned Rosy-finches (&lt;em&gt;L. tephrocotis&lt;/em&gt;) visit bird feeders throughout Utah&amp;rsquo;s mountains, making them amenable to study using RFID technology. Bird feeders maintained at ski areas and mountain homes provide important sources of food for wintering Rosy-finches as well as convenient study sites. To fill the data gaps that currently limit effective management of Black Rosy-finch populations, a voluntary public/private partnership of biologists developed the Utah Black Rosy-finch Study. Over the past two winters, we have banded almost two hundred rosy-finches and feeders have logged tens of thousands of visits. These preliminary data are already providing exciting insights into the ecology of these species, including documenting one Gray-crowned Rosy-finch that visited two feeders separately by nearly 50km in a single day! For more information about this research, see the &lt;a href=&#34;project/blrf.md&#34;&gt;Black Rosy-finch&lt;/a&gt; project page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-information&#34;&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonter, D. N. &amp;amp; Bridge, E. S. 2011. Applications of radio frequency identification (RFID) in ornithological research: A review. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Field Ornithology&lt;/em&gt; 82, 1–10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bridge, E. S. &amp;amp; Bonter, D. N. 2011. A low-cost radio frequency identification device for ornithological research. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Field Ornithology&lt;/em&gt; 82, 52–59.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
