<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rushing Avian Ecology Lab</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Rushing Avian Ecology Lab</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Rushing Avian Ecology Lab</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passerina buntings</title>
      <link>/project/passerina/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/passerina/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Species in the genus &lt;em&gt;Passerina&lt;/em&gt; are among the most charismatic birds in North America. They are also ideally suited for studying the full-annual-cycle ecology of migratory songbirds because several species can be efficiently captured and monitored at bird feeders throughout the year. For the past several years, I have worked with colleagues from the Smithsonian Migratory Bird Center and the Cornell Lab of Ornithology to better understand the migration ecology, migratory connectivity, and winter distrubution of southeastern Painted Buntings (&lt;em&gt;Passerina ciris&lt;/em&gt;) across their breeding range. To date, we have deployed nearly 300 light-level geolocators on buntings at 6 study sites spanning the latitudinal distribution of this population (northern Florida to southern North Carolina). In the spring of 2019, we established a network of RFID-enabled bird feeders to collect encounter data from buntings at each of our study sites. These data will provide critical information about seasonal survival of Painted Buntings, as well as how survival varies spatially and seasonally.&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-photo-by-kim-savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/lazb.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Photo by Kim Savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/lazb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Photo by Kim Savides
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also starting in the spring of 2019, we expanded this research to include Lazuli Buntings (&lt;em&gt;Passerina amoeba&lt;/em&gt;) breeding in and around Logan, UT. This project uses similar tracking and RFID technologies to quantify migratory connectivity, molting/winter grounds, and survival of Lazuli Buntings along a large elevational gradient. During the summer of 2020, our 18 RFID feeders recorded over 300,000 visits by about 250 banded birds! These data are allowing us to quantify arrival and departure phenology of these populations with a high degree of precision and in the future will allow us to estimate survival and density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually we hope the data collected as part of these projects will provide insights into how breeding and non-breeding processes influence vital rates and population dynamics and whether life-history theory provides a cogent framework for understanding full annual cycle limitation in migratory birds. Stay tuned for exciting results coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code of conduct</title>
      <link>/features/coc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/features/coc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All members of the Rushing lab are expected to behave in a manner that promotes a healthy, inclusive working environment. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be kind to others. Treat members of the lab as you would want to be treated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep all communication appropriate for a professional audience. Sexual or discriminatory language and imagery is not appropriate at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do your part to create a respectful environment for everyone. Every member of this lab has something to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that your actions can inadvertently be injurious to others even if you do not intend them to be. If someone calls you out on your behavior, please listen to them, apologize, and learn from the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discrimination or harassment of any kind will not be tolerated. This includes but is not limited to discrimination based on: racial or ethnic background, citizenship status, religion, political affiliation, gender identity/expression, sexual orientation, dis/ability status, or appearance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any instances of inappropriate behavior should be reported to Clark Rushing or the the appropriate authorities immediately. All communications will be treated as confidential. Any lab member that is asked to stop inappropriate behavior is expected to comply immediately. Failure to comply will result referral to the appropriate University authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sexual-harassment-and-assualt&#34;&gt;Sexual harassment and assualt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Utah State University takes issues related to sexual harassment and assault very seriously. From the USU &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usu.edu/sexual-assault/index&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;sexual harassment webpage&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexual harassment is unwelcome sexual advances, requests for sexual favors, and other verbal or physical conduct of a sexual nature when:&lt;br&gt;
- Submission to such conduct is made either explicitly or implicitly a term or condition of an individual&amp;rsquo;s employment or status as a student in a course, program or activity.&lt;br&gt;
- Submission to or rejection of such conduct by an individual is used as the basis for employment or academic decisions affecting an individual.&lt;br&gt;
- Such conduct has the purpose or effect of unreasonably interfering with an individual&amp;rsquo;s work or academic performance, or of creating an intimidating, hostile or offensive environment for working or learning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexual assault is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any type of sexual contact that occurs without the explicit consent of the recipient. It can range from unwanted sexual touching to rape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can report cases of sexual assault or harassment by clicking on the red &lt;code&gt;File a Report&lt;/code&gt; button &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usu.edu/sexual-assault/index&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that when reporting incidents of sexual assault or harassment, USU offers amnesty for the drug and alcohol student code violations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material in this document was inspired by and borrows from the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BahlaiLab/Policies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bahlai Lab Policies&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; by Dr. Christie Bahlai and her lab group, used under CC BY 4.0. The Rushing Lab policies are licensed under CC BY 4.0 by Dr. Clark Rushing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code of conduct</title>
      <link>/links/coc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/links/coc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All members of the Rushing lab are expected to behave in a manner that promotes a healthy, inclusive working environment. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be kind to others. Treat members of the lab as you would want to be treated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep all communication appropriate for a professional audience. Sexual or discriminatory language and imagery is not appropriate at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do your part to create a respectful environment for everyone. Every member of this lab has something to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that your actions can inadvertently be injurious to others even if you do not intend them to be. If someone calls you out on your behavior, please listen to them, apologize, and learn from the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discrimination or harassment of any kind will not be tolerated. This includes but is not limited to discrimination based on: racial or ethnic background, citizenship status, religion, political affiliation, gender identity/expression, sexual orientation, dis/ability status, or appearance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any instances of inappropriate behavior should be reported to Clark Rushing or the the appropriate authorities immediately. All communications will be treated as confidential. Any lab member that is asked to stop inappropriate behavior is expected to comply immediately. Failure to comply will result referral to the appropriate University authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sexual-harassment-and-assualt&#34;&gt;Sexual harassment and assualt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Georgia takes issues related to sexual harassment and assault very seriously. From the UGA &lt;a href=&#34;https://eoo.uga.edu/policies-resources/ndah-policy/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;non-discrimination and anti-harassment policy webpage&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sexual Misconduct&lt;/strong&gt;:  An umbrella term that is used to describe a wide range of prohibited sexual conduct as described below, including sexual harassment. Sexual misconduct can occur regardless of the relationship, position or respective sex, sexual orientation, or gender identity of the parties. Same-sex harassment violates this Policy, as does harassment by a student of an employee or a subordinate employee of their supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sexual Harassment&lt;/strong&gt; (Other than Student on Student): Unwelcome verbal, nonverbal, or physical conduct, based on sex (including gender stereotypes), that may be any of the following:
- Implicitly or explicitly a term or condition of employment or status in a course, program, or activity;
- A basis for employment or educational decisions;
- Is sufficiently severe, persistent, or pervasive to interfere with one’s work or educational performance creating an intimidating, hostile, or offensive work or learning environment, or interfering with or limiting one’s ability to participate in or to benefit from an institutional program or activity; or
- Determined by a Reasonable Person to be so severe, pervasive, and objectively offensive that it effectively denies a person equal access to a University education program or activity in violation of Title IX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sexual Harassment&lt;/strong&gt; (Student on Student): Unwelcome verbal, nonverbal, or physical conduct based on sex (including gender stereotypes), determined by a Reasonable Person to be so severe, pervasive, and objectively offensive that it effectively denies a person equal access to participate in or to benefit from an institutional education program or activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about how to report a sexual assault incident and resources if you have been the victim of sexual assault, please refer to the University&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://safeandsecure.uga.edu/sexual-assault/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Preventing and Responding to Sexual Assault&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that when reporting incidents of sexual assault or harassment, UGA &lt;a href=&#34;https://eoo.uga.edu/policies-resources/title-ix-sex-discrimination-harassment/sexual-assault-response-protocol/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;offers amnesty&lt;/a&gt; for the drug and alcohol student code violations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material in this document was inspired by and borrows from the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BahlaiLab/Policies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bahlai Lab Policies&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; by Dr. Christie Bahlai and her lab group, used under CC BY 4.0. The Rushing Lab policies are licensed under CC BY 4.0 by Dr. Clark Rushing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mentoring philosophy</title>
      <link>/links/mentoring_philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/links/mentoring_philosophy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No matter where you are in your career, academia can feel a bit like back-country orienteering. You pick a destination far off in the distance, make a plan for getting there, and then set off into the wilderness. In some places, especially early on, there may be well-worn trails. But as you go further, you will increasingly have to blaze your own path. The going is often tough. There may be times when you need to stop, figure out where you are, and reassess your plans. But with planning and a good support system, most destinations can be reached and the journey will be worth the effort. Although cheesy, I think this metaphor provides a good basis for my mentoring philosophy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-role&#34;&gt;My role&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe strongly that as an adviser, my job is to help students figure out where they want to go, to equip them with the right tools to get there, and to make sure they don&amp;rsquo;t get too lost along the way. My job is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to choose my students&#39; destinations for them or enforce a specific path. To this end, I strive to work with each lab member to establish long-term ambitions, shorter-term goals, and a roadmap for achieving these objectives. The degree of assistance that each student needs will vary as a function of previous experience, career goals, and self-sufficiency. Regardless, my primary role is to understand the needs of my students and provide them with the support they require to advance their career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course my career, I have found that my most productive relationships are based on respect, humility, hard work, and humor. These are traits that I strive to bring to the lab. They are also the traits I look for in collaborators and students. Members of my lab can expect me to provide a supportive, respectful working environment and above all I expect all lab members to &lt;a href=&#34;links/code-of-conduct.html&#34;&gt;contribute positively&lt;/a&gt; to this atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-docs&#34;&gt;Post-docs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-docs are at a transitional phase in their career: still under the supervision of a mentor but expected to demonstrate the ability to conduct research as an independent scientist. The primary purpose of doing a post-doc is, in my opinion, to get a permanent job, not to pad the CV of your mentor. Therefore, I view post-docs in may lab as collaborators rather than employees or students. Early in your post-doc, we will establish a set of deliverables for the project that is funding your fellowship and a plan for carrying out the research. We will also discuss your career goals and identify opportunities to strengthen your CV in areas that will help you land a job. I may lean on you from time-to-time to help with teaching or mentoring duties but you should focus first and foremost on publishing papers, getting grants, and applying for jobs. Where applicable, we will work together to design new projects and find additional funding. If at any point during your post-doc you get offered a job that you want, TAKE IT! Whatever project you&amp;rsquo;re working on for me will survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;graduate-students&#34;&gt;Graduate students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expectations for graduate students enrolled in Warnell&amp;rsquo;s MS and PhD programs are outlined in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.warnell.uga.edu/graduate/current-students/advisory-committee-and-program-study&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;graduate student handbook&lt;/a&gt;. This document also contains useful information and advice for being successful in this department. Additional resources for completing your degree, including a checklist of degree completion requirements for both the MS and PhD programs, can be found on the School&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.warnell.uga.edu/sites/default/files/inline-files/PHD%20Checklist.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. This checklist will serve as the primary guide for developing individual expectations within the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the degree completion requirements, I recognize that individual students have different expectations and objectives both during and after graduate school. My role as a mentor is to help you formulate and meet those objectives. For this reason, I will meet with each student in my lab early in your first semester and then on a regular basis to discuss expectations, goals, and progress. During these meetings we will develop a mentoring plan that establishes shared objectives, timelines, and deliverables. This plan may (and will likely) change over the course of your graduate career but will serve as blueprint for us to establish your personal goals and a defined path for progress and evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;undergraduate-students&#34;&gt;Undergraduate students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting involved in on-going research projects or establishing independent projects with the help of a faculty mentor are great ways for undergraduates to gets hands-on research experience, deepen their understanding of scientific concepts, and become more competitive for jobs or graduate school.
I am happy to help interested students plan, implement, and communicate independent research projects. I plan to establish several local field projects that focus on the ecology of birds in and around Athens. These projects could provide numerous opportunities for independent research by students interested in ornithology, population ecology, behavior, and statistical modeling. If you are interested in the work done my lab and would like to get involved in undergraduate research, please contact me about research and funding opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-idwork_life_balanceaa-note-on-work-life-balance&#34;&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;work_life_balance&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A note on work-life balance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academia is stressful. Social isolation, imposter syndrome, and competitive job markets all contribute to high rates of mental health issues in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2018/03/06/new-study-says-graduate-students-mental-health-crisis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;graduate students&lt;/a&gt;. Although some stress is unavoidable, suffering from mental health issues is not inevitable. Spending time with family, finding activities that help you recharge your batteries, and taking time off are all important strategies for maintaining mental and physical health. These activities also tend to boost long-term productivity. One of the reasons for developing a individual mentoring plan is so that we can judge your progress based on explicit expectations and goals rather than proxies like hours spent in the lab. We will meet on a regular basis to make sure you are on the right track and I do expect students to make steady progress. However, as long as you are making progress towards your degree, when and how you work does not make much difference to me. If you work best early in the morning, late at night, or during the weekend, that&amp;rsquo;s fine. If you can get everything done M-Th, take long weekends. Bottom line, find the schedule that works best for you and go with it. I pledge to encourage members of my lab to have a healthy life outside of the office and to lead by example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also recognize that a healthy work-life balance may not, by itself, be enough. If you are in my lab and feel like you are struggling with mental health issues, please come talk to me. We will work together to find help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material in this document was inspired by and borrows from the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BahlaiLab/Policies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bahlai Lab Policies&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; by Dr. Christie Bahlai and her lab group, used under CC BY 4.0. The Rushing Lab policies are licensed under CC BY 4.0 by Dr. Clark Rushing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prospective students</title>
      <link>/links/prospective_students/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/links/prospective_students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;phd-assistantship-pinyon-jay-habitat-use-and-movement-ecology&#34;&gt;PhD assistantship, Pinyon Jay habitat use and movement ecology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location – Athens, GA with fieldwork in Utah and New Mexico&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salary - $30,000 per year plus tuition, fees, and benefits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start Date – January 10th, 2022 (preferred)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last Date To Apply – September 24th, 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently seeking applicants for a PhD assistantship (4 years, fully funded) available in the Warnell School of Forestry and Natural Resources at the University of Georgia to study Pinyon Jay (&lt;em&gt;Gymnorhinus cyanocephalus&lt;/em&gt;) habitat use and movement ecology in response to piñon-juniper woodland treatments. Students from under-represented groups in wildlife fields are strongly encouraged to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Piñon-juniper woodland treatments are common throughout the western United States, though the effects of these treatments on Pinyon Jays, a species undergoing rapid population declines across its range, are poorly understood. This study will provide land management agencies critical information about impacts of woodland management on Pinyon Jays, as well as produce significant, novel data about habitat use, movement, and life history of the species. These data will allow land managers to better understand the needs of the species and inform how future management practices can be implemented to reduce or mitigate negative impacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The selected student will be expected to conduct fieldwork at multiple locations throughout the state of Utah and northern New Mexico. Fieldwork will include: conducting grid-based point counts, capturing and banding jays, deploying tracking tags using conventional harness-style attachments, and possibly performing colony counts. The student will also be expected the analyze multiple types of data using modern statistical methods and communicate project results to multiple audiences, including the scientific community, agency staff, and the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preference will be given to candidates who can enroll for the spring 2022 semester. The successful applicant will receive a $30,000 per year stipend (12-month). Tuition is also covered and the student will receive either direct bill payments or a stipend supplement to cover at least 75% of the student portion of university fees and health insurance. The student will be advised by Dr. Clark Rushing at the University of Georgia, while working closely with collaborators at the Utah Division of Wildlife Resources and the US Fish &amp;amp; Wildlife Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;qualifications&#34;&gt;Qualifications:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B.S. degree in wildlife biology, management, ecology, or related discipline&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.S. degree in wildlife biology, management, ecology, or related discipline strongly preferred.  GRE scores are not required&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrated experience capturing and banding birds, including attachment of tracking tags&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrated experience collecting and analyzing ecological data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excellent written and verbal communication skills&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong interest in quantitative techniques and spatial ecology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experience in R is strongly preferred&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this position will require the ability to legally operate state-owned vehicles in off-road conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested applicants should submit the following documents as a single PDF or word document to Dr. Clark Rushing (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:clark.rushing@uga.edu&#34;&gt;clark.rushing@uga.edu&lt;/a&gt;) by September 24th, 2021:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.5-page (max) cover letter summarizing your interest in the position, qualifications, and experience, as well as research and career aspirations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curriculum Vitae&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An applicant-led writing sample (e.g., thesis chapter, publication)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unofficial academic transcripts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Names and contact information for three professional references&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, students with their own funding are welcome to reach out to me about joining the lab. I am happy to advise students working on a variety of topics related to ornithology, quantitative ecology, and conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-note-on-quantitative-skills-for-prospective-students&#34;&gt;A note on quantitative skills for prospective students&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecology is an inherently quantitative field and it is becoming nearly impossible to be a practicing ecologist without some training in statistics and programming. The research done in my lab reflects these realities and I want all of my students to graduate with a toolbox of quantitative skills that will allow them to be successful professionals. I do not, however, require new students to arrive on campus with extensive experience in these areas. More important to me is a desire to learn quantitative skills and apply them to exciting scientific questions. At the end of the day, if you can formulate good questions and are willing to put in the time to learn how to answer them, you will be a successful scientist. So if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the types of questions that we ask in the Rushing lab but don&amp;rsquo;t consider yourself a quantitative ecologist, don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to contact me about joining the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Black Rosy-finches</title>
      <link>/project/blrf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/blrf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Black Rosy-finch (&lt;em&gt;Leucosticte atrata&lt;/em&gt;) are one of the least understood birds in North America. Climate change threatens their high-elevation breeding habitat and very little is known about their life history, making them a high priority for conservation. The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Partners in Flight, Utah Division of Wildlife Resources, and U.S. Forest Service identify Black Rosy-finch as a species of conservation concern. A significant hurdle in understanding threats to the Black Rosy-finch and its future well-being is an absence of the most basic life history and demography information. The lack of data limits effective conservation actions critical to ensuring that populations can be sustained, even in the face of threats like climate change. The &lt;strong&gt;Utah Black Rosy-finch Study&lt;/strong&gt; was developed to fill these data gaps, make recommendations based on the data, and conserve the Black Rosy-finch. The project is a voluntary partnership between Utah State University, Tracy Aviary, Wild Utah Project, Utah Division of Wildlife Resources, Department of Defense, and the U.S. Forest Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to understand the life history requirements and demography of Black Rosy-finch in Utah to ensure this species persists into the future, while providing data to managers and practitioners through the specie’s range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tracking-rosy-finches-using-rfid&#34;&gt;Tracking Rosy-finches using RFID&lt;/h2&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-pit-tagged-black-rosy-finch-photo-courtesy-of-kim-savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/blrf_band.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;PIT tagged Black Rosy-finch. Photo courtesy of Kim Savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/blrf_band.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    PIT tagged Black Rosy-finch. Photo courtesy of Kim Savides
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2019, we have been using RFID-enabled bird feeders to collect encounter data of wintering Black Rosy-finches in northern Utah. The study focuses on bird feeders maintained at ski areas, nature centers, and private residences in northern Utah. Mountain sites provide food for wintering finches, as well as accessible places for data collection. During winter of 2019/2020, we recorded nearly 12,000 visits by 91 tagged Black and Gray-crowned Rosy-finches, including three Black Rosy-finches that were originally banded during the pilot 2019 season. Preliminary analysis of these data suggest that these sites may be used by multiple populations of finches, including over-wintering residents and spring migrants passing through on their way to the breeding grounds. As of November 2020, at least 5 banded birds have been re-sighted at our study sites and we will soon be recording these birds at the RFID feeders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, these data will allow us to estimate important demographic parameters, including survival, migratory phenology, winter site fidelity, and movement rates. When combined with counts of Rosy-finches across their winter range, these data will also provided critical information about the distribution and abundance of Rosy-finches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;community-science-counts&#34;&gt;Community science counts&lt;/h2&gt;








  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/blrf_logo.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/blrf_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining a network of RFID feeders in the harsh conditions that Rosy-finches inhabit during the winter prevents widespread adoption of this method across the entire range. To supplement data from the RFID feeders and to be better understand the distribution and habitat requirements of wintering Rosy-finches, we initiated a community science project in 2019 that aims to build a network of volunteers to count Rosy-finches throughout the Intermountain West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With assitance from the Wild Utah Project and Tracy Aviary, &lt;a href=&#34;/content/authors/KSavides/index.md&#34;&gt; Kim Savides &lt;/a&gt; has developed a workshop to train volunteers regarding  the objective of the project, how to collect and submit data, identification tips, and strategies for counting flocks of Rosy-finches. Once trained, volunteers conduct 5-7 20-minute counts during pre-defined sampling windows running from January to April. During counts, volunteers record all Rosy-finches seen around their feeder, providing us with critical information about where and when these species occur during the winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first winter season of this project (2019/2020), volunteers conducted a total of 118 feeder surveys at 17 locations in northern Utah. As of November 2020, over 225 volunteers have signed up to conduct counts during the 2020/2021 season, expanding the scope of our sampling to include Colorado, Wyoming, New Mexico, and Idaho. Stay tuned for more results from this exciting project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about counting Rosy-finches, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wildutahproject.org/rosy-finch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;project website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate change</title>
      <link>/project/climatechange/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/climatechange/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have several on going projects focused on developing quantitative methods to measure the impacts of climate change on the distributions of North American birds and to incorporate this information into conservation decisions made by federal agencies. A major aim of this research is using data from the North American Breeding Bird Survey to create multi-species indices of climate-induced range shifts. This approach uses dynamic occupancy models to estimate range-wide occupancy and extinction/colonization rates for individual species. By accounting for both non-equilibrium dynamics and imperfect detection, these models provide robust estimates of the velocity, magnitude, and direction of range shifts that have occurred in recent decades. Results from individual species can be combined into composite metrics, which allow stronger inferences about climate change impacts and can be used to test hypotheses about the traits that influence sensitivity to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many federal agencies are tasked with protecting North America’s avian diversity and these agencies must make sound decisions about when and where to invest resources to achieve their legal mandates. Climate change adds a major source of uncertainty to these decisions because the places that are important for conservation now may differ from the critical locations in the future. Along with my work on modeling climate-driven range shifts, I am interested in incorporating climate change into management decisions and research prioritization to improve migratory bird conservation in the face of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;relevant-publications-pdf-available-upon-request&#34;&gt;Relevant publications (pdf available upon request):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Royle, J.A., Ziolkowski, D., Pardieck, K., (2019). Estimating spatially and temporally complex range dynamics when detection is imperfect. &lt;em&gt;Scientific Reports&lt;/em&gt; 9(1), 1-9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C. S., Royle, J. A., Ziolkowski, D. J., &amp;amp; Pardieck, K. L. (2020). Migratory behavior and winter geography drive differential range shifts of eastern birds in response to recent climate change. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 117(23), 12897-12903.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C. S., Rubenstein, M., Lyons, J. E., &amp;amp; Runge, M. C. (2020). Using value of information to prioritize research needs for migratory bird management under climate change: a case study using federal land acquisition in the United States. &lt;em&gt;Biological Reviews&lt;/em&gt; 95(4), 1109-1130.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Full annual cycle models</title>
      <link>/project/fac/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/fac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Historically, efforts to identify limiting factors for migratory species have been hindered by the scale of annual migration movements, missing information about the geographic linkages between breeding and non-breeding populations (i.e., migratory connectivity), and the lack of analytical methods for linking population dynamics to demographic processes operating across the entire annual cycle. A major theme of my research focuses on application technological advances and developing ‘full-annual-cycle’ population models to overcome these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major challenges to understanding limiting factors of migratory birds has long been the scientists have not known where specific populations go after they leave the breeding or wintering grounds. Information about migration routes, winter distribution, and migration phenology is currently unavailable for many species because, until recently, over 40% of migratory bird species were too small track using even the most advanced satellite tags. A major focus of my research has been using new technologies, including stable isotopes (Rushing et al. 2014 Ecol Apps; Rushing et al. 2017 Ecol &amp;amp; Evol) and miniaturized tracking tags, to better understand the migratory connectivity of small songbirds (Cohen et al. 2018 MEE). Current work on this topic includes two projects that are using light-level geolocators to determine the migratory connectivity and non-breeding distribution of &lt;a href=&#34;project/passerina.md&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Passerina&lt;/em&gt; buntings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to quantifying patterns of migratory connectivity, much of my research focuses on developing &amp;lsquo;full-annual-cycle&amp;rsquo; models to link population dynamics of migratory birds to demographic and environmental processes occurring through the year. Full-annual-cycle models include a broad range of modeling frameworks (Hosttetler et al. 2015) and I regularly use several of these methods in my research, including Bayesian hierarchical models and integrated population models (IPMs). Some of my work on full-annual-cycle models has focused on exploring how breeding vs. winter habitat contribute to spatial variation in population trajectories in Wood Thrush (Rushing et al. 2016b Proc B), estimating seasonal survival rates by integrating breeding and winter capture-recapture data (Rushing 2019 Ecol &amp;amp; Evol), and using IPMs to link changes in Wood Thrush breeding abundance to reproduction, immigration and seasonal survival (Rushing et al. 2017b Ecology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the importance of full-annual-cycle models for advancing our understanding of the ecology of migratory birds, continued work on developing and expanding these frameworks is the central aim of my current research. Ongoing projects on this topic include: improving methods to estimate fall and spring migration survival and their relation to climate, habitat, and density; developing population viability analyses that can used to predict the effects of breeding vs. non-breeding management options; and developing a theoretical framework for predicting when and why populations should be breeding vs. non-breeding limited. In the coming years, our projects on migratory connectivity and variation in life-history strategies of &lt;em&gt;Passerina&lt;/em&gt; buntings will produce data for testing these theoretical predictions. Ultimately, it is my hope that these efforts can be used to improve management and conservation outcomes for the many species of declining migratory birds across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;relevant-publications-pdf-available-upon-request&#34;&gt;Relevant publications (pdf available upon request):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C. S. 2019. Estimability of migration survival rates from integrated breeding and winter capture–recapture data. &lt;em&gt;Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, 9(2), 849-858.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Hostetler, J.A., Sillett, T.S., Marra, P.P., Rotenberg, J.A. and Ryder, T.B., 2017. Spatial and temporal drivers of avian population dynamics across the annual cycle. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt;, 98(11), 2837-2850.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Ryder, T.B. and Marra, P.P., 2016. Quantifying drivers of population dynamics for a migratory bird throughout the annual cycle. &lt;em&gt;Proc. R. Soc. B&lt;/em&gt;, 283(1823), 20152846.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Ryder, T.B., Saracco, J.F. and Marra, P.P., 2014. Assessing migratory connectivity for a long‐distance migratory bird using multiple intrinsic markers. &lt;em&gt;Ecological Applications&lt;/em&gt;, 24(3), 445-456.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen, E.B., Hostetler, J.A., Hallworth, M.T., Rushing, C.S., Sillett, T.S. and Marra, P.P., 2018. Quantifying the strength of migratory connectivity. &lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;, 9(3), 513-524.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen, E.B., Rushing, C.R., Moore, F.R., Hallworth, M.T., Hostetler, J.A., Ramirez, M.G. and Marra, P.P., 2018. The strength of migratory connectivity for birds en route to breeding through the Gulf of Mexico. &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long-distance dispersal</title>
      <link>/project/dispersal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dispersal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Immigration and emigration (collectively termed &lt;em&gt;dispersal&lt;/em&gt;) are key demographic processes influencing both individual fitness and population dynamics. Many dispersal movements happen at spatial scales much larger than the boundaries of typical study areas but due to the challenges of tracking dispersing individuals, the causes and consequences of these movements are poorly understood. A primary focus of my research is developing analytical tools to study the individual- and population-level consequences of long-distance dispersal. Much of my research on long-distance dispersal has focused on using stable isotopes, particularly hydrogen, to detect long-distance dispersal movements and quantify how they influence individual fitness. More recently, my research on this topic has focused on the intersection between habitat selection, dispersal distance, and population dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;relevant-publications-pdf-available-upon-request&#34;&gt;Relevant publications (pdf available upon request):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Marra, P.P. and Dudash, M.R., 2016. Winter habitat quality but not long‐distance dispersal influences apparent reproductive success in a migratory bird. &lt;em&gt;Ecology&lt;/em&gt;, 97(5), 1218-1227.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Dudash, M.R., Studds, C.E. and Marra, P.P., 2015. Annual variation in long‐distance dispersal driven by breeding and non‐breeding season climatic conditions in a migratory bird. &lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt;, 38(10), 1006-1014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesson, S.V., Okamura, B., Dudaniec, R.Y., Vyverman, W., Löndahl, J., Rushing, C., Valentini, A. and Green, A.J., 2015. Integrating microorganism and macroorganism dispersal: modes, techniques and challenges with particular focus on co-dispersal. &lt;em&gt;Écoscience&lt;/em&gt;, 22(2-4), 109-124.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rushing, C.S., Dudash, M.R. and Marra, P.P., 2015. Habitat features and long‐distance dispersal modify the use of social information by a long‐distance migratory bird. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Animal Ecology&lt;/em&gt;, 84(6), 1469-1479.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pelicans</title>
      <link>/project/pelicans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pelicans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Great Salt Lake is home to the largest to third largest American white pelican colony west of the Rocky
Mountains. This colony breeds on Gunnison Island, a small island in the
hypersaline northern arm of the lake. This part of the lake is devoid of fresh water
and fish, and breeding white pelicans must travel approximately 50km to the nearest foraging
area to gather food for their chicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gunnison pelicans have a long history of study, with breeding colony counts beginning as early as
1963, intensive study of nesting behavior by USU graduate and prominent ornithologist Fritz
Knopf in the 1970s, and fledgling banding efforts by the Utah Department of Wildlife Resources
(UDWR) beginning in 2009. The UDWR also began deploying GPS transmitters on adult white
pelicans in 2015, and are in the process of expanding pelican movement data collection with
construction of a new Motus network around the Great Salt Lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently collaborating with UDWR on several projects to better understand the demography, movement, and dynamics of this regionally important colony of white pelicans. This work is being led by PhD student &lt;a href=&#34;authors/AVanTatenhove.md&#34;&gt;Aimee Van Tatenhove&lt;/a&gt;, who is supported by an endowed fellowship gifted to USU by Fritz Knopf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;current-american-white-pelican-projects-at-the-rushing-lab&#34;&gt;Current American white pelican projects at the Rushing Lab&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;habitat-selection-and-niche-switching-between-summer-and-winter-ranges&#34;&gt;Habitat selection and niche switching between summer and winter ranges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using GPS telemetry data from birds tagged around the Great Salt Lake, this project aims to
identify important white pelican habitat on the breeding and wintering grounds, and assess
niche breadth and niche-switching behavior to explore potential pelican response to climate
change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;historical-spatio-temporal-survival-and-migratory-connectivity&#34;&gt;Historical spatio-temporal survival and migratory connectivity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using long-term banding data from the USGS Bird Banding Laboratory, this research will estimate white
pelican survival over the past 60 years and explore survival pre- and post-organochloride
pesticide bans. We will also assess migratory connectivity between breeding and wintering
regions, to inform management practices at a continental scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;airspace-use-through-radar-detections-and-gps-telemetry&#34;&gt;Airspace use through radar detections and GPS telemetry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using radar and GPS telemetry data, this project is exploring the ability of detect and identify pelicans using Nexrad radar images from
around the Great Salt Lake. We are currently testing the viability of radar to quantify white pelican airspace use
and phenology without GPS transmitter deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;environmental-drivers-of-historical-utah-breeding-colony-counts&#34;&gt;Environmental drivers of historical Utah breeding colony counts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research will identify potential drivers of annual white pelican colony counts on Gunnison Island, including temperature, precipitation, and Great Salt
Lake water levels, to inform management decisions and suggest important future population drivers of the Gunnison
breeding colony.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RFID</title>
      <link>/project/rfid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/rfid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, studying individual birds has been a labor-intensive process. Individuals must be captured, given unique marks (e.g., metal and colored plastic leg bands), and then re-captured or re-sighted during future study periods. Re-capturing and re-sighting efforts, in particular, tend to be expensive, time-consumiing, and often have low detection probabilities. A growing part our lab&amp;rsquo;s research is focused on the use of Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) technology to overcome these obstacles and advance our understanding of the demography and behavior of migratory birds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-is-rfid&#34;&gt;What is RFID?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio-frequency_identification&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RFID&lt;/a&gt; is a widespread technology that uses electromagnetic fields to identify coded tags that are attached to individual organisms or objects. It is the exact same technology that is used to chip pets and record times in a marathon. RFID networks consist of four components: 1) a transponder tag attached to each individual, 2) an antenna for receiving data from each transponder tag, 3) a tag-reading device that interprets and logs the data from each tag, and 4) a power source. In most wildlife studies that use RFID, the reader, antenna, and power source are placed in a location where individuals from the study population will reliably visit. Individuals are marked with passive integrated transponder (PIT) tags, which provide a unique ID code for each individual. When marked individuals are within range of the antenna, the reader logs the ID and time of the visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-do-you-use-rfid-to-study-birds&#34;&gt;How do you use RFID to study birds?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RFID networks used in most ornithogical research have relatively small read ranges (~2-6cm). As a result, use of this technology requires placing the antenna and reader in a location that birds are likely to visit, including nest boxes and bird feeders. For our research, we have specially chosen several species that regularly visit bird feeders during either their breeding or winter period. This allows us to locate the RFID antennas on the feeder perches, ensuring that individuals will be within a few centimeters of the antenna while they eat. The reader and a small battery are housed under or next to the feeder in a waterproof box and a solar panel is attached to the feeder stand to provide continuous power.&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-rfid-feeder&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/feeder.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;RFID feeder&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/feeder.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    RFID feeder
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because PIT tags need no battery, they are small and widely available as bird bands. Once the RFID network is installed on a feeder, we band individual birds using that feeder, giving each bird an aluminum USGS band and a PIT band. Both bands have a unique numeric code (physically etched into the metal band, stored as part of the transponder in the PIT band), allowing us to individually identify each bird when we encounter it at future points in time. &lt;strong&gt;Please be aware that all banding activities, including capturing birds and attaching auxillary leg bands, are carried out by trained professionals with all state and federal permits&lt;/strong&gt;. After a bird is banded, it is released unharmed and the reader will log every subsequent visit that individual makes to the feeder. These &amp;ldquo;encounter histories&amp;rdquo; provide data that can be used to estimate ecological parameters that are central to our research questions (e.g., survival probability, arrival/departure dates, activity levels, etc.) using well-established statistical models.&lt;/p&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-pit-tagged-lazuli-bunting-photo-by-kim-savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/rfid_lazb.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;PIT tagged Lazuli Bunting. Photo by Kim Savides&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/rfid_lazb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    PIT tagged Lazuli Bunting. Photo by Kim Savides
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rfid-projects-in-our-lab&#34;&gt;RFID projects in our lab&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;painted-buntings&#34;&gt;Painted Buntings&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2019, we installed RFID feeders at several of long-term Painted Bunting (&lt;em&gt;Passerina ciris&lt;/em&gt;) field sites in Florida, Georgia, South Carolina, and North Carolina. Over the next two summers, these feeders logged nearly 100,000 unique visits by about 150 tagged individuals. In the future, we plan to expand this feeder network within and beyond these sites to better understand survival, phenology, and density of Painted Buntings within the eastern population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lazuli-buntings&#34;&gt;Lazuli Buntings&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Painted Buntings, the closely-related Lazuli Bunting (&lt;em&gt;Passerina amoena&lt;/em&gt;) is one of the most charismatic migratory birds in the American West. In autumn, individuals migrate to northern Mexico where they molt during monsoonal rains before moving further south for the winter. Lazuli Buntings are also one of the most common migratory songbirds breeding in Cache Valley, Utah and can be found across a wide elevational range, from the valley floor (~1400m) to the high peaks of the Bear River Range (~3000m). During the spring and summer of 2019, we established a network of RFID feeders at 3 sites that span this elevational gradient. During the summers of 2019 and 2020, these feeders recorded nearly 400,000 unique visits by several hundred banded buntings. We are currently using these data to estimate elevational variation in the migration phenology of male and female buntings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;black-rosy-finches&#34;&gt;Black Rosy-finches&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black Rosy-finches (&lt;em&gt;Leucosticte atrata&lt;/em&gt;) are one of three species of Rosy-finch in North America. Utah is at the heart of the Black Rosy-finch distribution. Due to their small range and inaccessible breeding habitat, Black Rosy-finches are one of the least-studied birds in North America. As such, the future well-being of Rosy-finches is hampered by an absence of even basic information about the demography, distribution, and movement of this species. Filling crucial data gaps about Black Rosy-finches distribution and abundance is especially critical to ensure that their populations can be sustained in the face of habitat degradation and climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In winter, flocks of Black Rosy-finches and Gray-crowned Rosy-finches (&lt;em&gt;L. tephrocotis&lt;/em&gt;) visit bird feeders throughout Utah&amp;rsquo;s mountains, making them amenable to study using RFID technology. Bird feeders maintained at ski areas and mountain homes provide important sources of food for wintering Rosy-finches as well as convenient study sites. To fill the data gaps that currently limit effective management of Black Rosy-finch populations, a voluntary public/private partnership of biologists developed the Utah Black Rosy-finch Study. Over the past two winters, we have banded almost two hundred rosy-finches and feeders have logged tens of thousands of visits. These preliminary data are already providing exciting insights into the ecology of these species, including documenting one Gray-crowned Rosy-finch that visited two feeders separately by nearly 50km in a single day! For more information about this research, see the &lt;a href=&#34;project/blrf.md&#34;&gt;Black Rosy-finch&lt;/a&gt; project page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-information&#34;&gt;Further information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonter, D. N. &amp;amp; Bridge, E. S. 2011. Applications of radio frequency identification (RFID) in ornithological research: A review. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Field Ornithology&lt;/em&gt; 82, 1–10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bridge, E. S. &amp;amp; Bonter, D. N. 2011. A low-cost radio frequency identification device for ornithological research. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Field Ornithology&lt;/em&gt; 82, 52–59.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
